以射手网英文字幕为基础添加简体中文字幕
（作者/LuLu）
“战争中首先牺牲的是真相”
-美国参议员 海勒姆.约翰逊 1918年
《五日战争》
本片根据真实故事改编
Based on actual events
在过去的10年中，有500多名战地记者丧生
More than 500 war reporters were killed in the last decade.
谨以此片纪念他们
This film is dedicated to their memory.
伊拉克 2007年
Iraq - 2007
他不会说话，所以他只能拍东西
He can't talk,so he just films things.
是 差不多
Yeah, basically.
还给他的摄像机取名儿，我觉得挺可怜的
He's even named his camera Dave,which I find kind of sad.
我们开拍了
And we're taping.
安德斯 玛丽安
Anders. Miriam.
向家乡的朋友们问个好
Say hello to the folks at home.
说“来自地狱的问候”来吧
Say, "Greetings from hell."Come on, guys.
你们在后面做什么呢？计划约会？
What are you doing back there?Planning a date?
我们在想为什么艾尔.莎非会同意我们去采访他
We're speculating about al-Safi's motives on giving us this interview.
是啊，我们来说点大家感兴趣的吧
Yeah. Let's talk about something that really interests people.
比如夫妻生活
Like sex.
赛伯延 你真是个变态！
Sebastian, you are such a fucking pervert!
为什么不关上机器，省些电留着拍正经的呢？
Why don't you turn that off, and save the battery for the real stuff?
- 就是，别拍我们了！- 这就是正经的啊
- Yeah, stop filming us! - This is the real stuff.
无聊又老套的战争哪有人关心
People don't care about boring old war.
得来点刺激的转移一下他们对【美国偶像】的兴趣
They need something juicy to break away from "American Idol".
像是记者们的紧急夫妻生活报道
Like emergency sex among reporters.
安德斯，你能给电视观众解释一下这个的概念吗？
Anders, would you care to explain that concept to TV audiences?
你为什么不解释一下？
Why don't you explain it?
你晚上不也是一个人在网上
You can explain the emergency sex you have at night,
跟网络紧急夫妻生活吗
alone with the internet, you know.
我们可不想在你的性福生活节目里谈我们的夫妻生活
Cos we don't want our sex lives on your emergency sex show.
哦，小姐！ 你说的是“你们的夫妻生活”？
Whoa there, missy! Did you just say, "Our sex lives"?
啊 那确实是有这回事了？
Ah, does that mean you guys are finally doing it?
回去以后我们得好好谈谈
When we get home we're gonna have a talk
你好缺乏职业道德啊，是不是？
about your lack of journalistic standards, OK?
你肯定会被狠狠地惩罚
You'll be severely disciplined.
我看到些东西 哪里?
I see something.Where?
-我看到有人在路上! -我什么都没看到!
- I see someone on the road! - I don't see anything!
靠!靠!靠!
Fuck! Fuck! Fuck!
我靠!天啊!关上车门!
Fuck! Jesus! Shut the door!
-大家都还好吗? -是的!趴下!
- Is everyone all right? - Yeah! Get down!
把车倒回去!
Get this car in reverse!
倒车啊!带我们离开这儿!通讯社!
Back off! Get us out of here! Press!
通讯社!
Press!
快倒车
Put the car in reverse!
快动起来,蠢货,不然我们都会死的!
Move it, motherfucker,or we're all dead!
带我们离开这儿!
Get us the fuck out of here!
-你还好吗? -没事,我想是打到防弹衣了
- Are you all right? - Yeah. I think the vest caught it.
她还好吗?严重吗?
Is she OK? Is it bad?
她腰部中弹了!她流了很多血!
She's been hit through the side! She's bleeding pretty bad!
和我待在一起!你和我待在一起!
Stay with me! You stay with me!
听着我说话!你听我说话!叫我的名字!
You keep listening to me! You keep
listening to me! Say my name!
哦,该死! 你会好起来的,有我在
- Oh, shit! - You're gonna be OK. I got you.
快带我们离开这儿!
Get us the fuck out of here!
我们会带你离开这儿的,好吗?只要和我在一起!
We're gonna get you out of here, OK? Just stay with me!
-我操！ -天啊！
- Fuck! - Jesus!
别走..不要走！玛丽安！
Don't you go... Don't you go anywhere! Miriam!
我操！
Fuck!
玛丽安！
Miriam!
建立防线
Defensive positions!
嘿，你们先救她，好吗？
Hey, you have to help her first, OK?
联络救护，准备两台紧急手术！
Call for medevac! Two urgent surgicals!
我们走！来吧！
Let's go! Come on!
你们是哪儿的？ -格鲁吉亚！联军！
- Where are you guys from? - Georgia! Coalition forces!
小心！火箭弹 12点钟方向！
Look out! RPG at 12 o'clock!
（米-24“雌鹿”武装直升机）
它曾救过我的命
This saved my life once.
洛杉矶 一年后
Los Angeles - One year later
这些天
'These days,
（冲突地区的暴力行为不断升级）
'violence in the conflict zone has continued to escalate,
（已经明显威胁到我地区的和平）
'and now represents a clear threat to peace in our region.
（这里是高加索地区，暴力行为会危及到每个人）
'This is the Caucasus,where violence harms everyone.
（我请求独立派，俄罗斯联邦）
'I plead to the separatists,the Russian Federation,
（与格鲁吉亚人民）
'and the people of Georgia,
（重新坐下来谈判）
'let's return to the negotiating table.
（刚刚是格鲁吉亚总统萨卡什维利的讲话）
'That was Georgian President, Mikheil Saakashvili,
（他正在努力拉近格鲁吉亚和西方国家的关系）
'who is struggling to move his country closer to the West.
（这个前苏联成员国曾向伊拉克和阿富汗派兵）
'This former Soviet republic has already sent troops
（支持北约在该地区的行动）
'to assist NATO's missions in Iraq and Afghanistan,
（并希望成为北约和欧盟的正式成员国）
'and would like full membership in both NATO and the EU.
（苏联解体后，俄罗斯仍然希望重新控制）
'Not surprisingly, Georgia's aspiration to integrate with the West
（它所失去的领土，这显然与格鲁吉亚）
'is in direct conflict with Russia's desire to regain influence
（与西方联盟的意愿相冲突）
'over territory lost in the break-up of the Soviet Union,
（俄罗斯领导人弗拉基米尔.普京认为）
'which according to Russia's leader, Vladimir Putin,
（苏联的解体是20世纪地缘政治上的最大灾难）
'was the greatest geopolitical catastrophe of the 20th century.'
那么，怎么样？
So, what's going on?
这整个地方要消失了，伙计，一个人都没有
'This place is about to blow, man. There's no one here.
除了我，佐伊和斯蒂尔顿，格鲁吉亚已经没人了
'There's no one in Georgia,but me Zoe and Stilton.
今天还有辆警车被烧
'Just today there was a police truck, got lit up.
有人在边界对维护部队开火
'The peacekeepers have come under fire on the border.'
哦，那条边界是..
Whoa. That's the border...
与南奥塞梯的共治边界
'The administrative border with South Ossetia.
那两个要搞分裂的省份之一，后台是俄罗斯
'Lt's one of two breakaway provinces backed by the Russians.
90年代初战争爆发以来
'Both sides have had peacekeepers here
双方都有维护部队驻扎在那里
'since war broke out here in the early 90s.'
保险公司不愿意给我承保.我不去了
No one'll fucking insure me.I can't.
从伊拉克回来后我就落下了坏名声
I got a special reputation after Iraq and...
确实，我以前太胡作非为了
Apparently,I was a loose cannon before.
-你确实很胡作非为 -谢谢
- 'You are a loose cannon.' - Thanks.
听着，我不关心你怎么做
'Listen, I don't care what you do.
去找个医生给你开证明，赶紧过来
'Get onto a doc, get your papers and get over here.'
我知道赛伯延早就想行动了
I know Sebastian's ready to rock and roll.
我会给你跳舞的
'I will dance for you!'
（达奇曼已退出通话）
格鲁吉亚 首都 第比利斯 - 2008年8月6日
Tbilisi, Georgia - August 6, 2008
这看起来不错啊
It looks nice.
在被战争摧毁之前，大部分地方都不错
Then again most places do before war tears 'em up.
但最后都回变成一个样，世界连眼都不带眨的
In the end they all look the same.And the world barely blinks.
这就是我错过的
There's that cheer I was missing
我只是实话实说罢了
I'm just laying out the facts.
五大洲都要有种族屠杀了
There could be genocides on five continents,
人们却全不在乎
people don't give a fuck.
到时候上帝都不会派人救他们
God forbid their cable goes out, though.
那么俄罗斯干嘛来这里凑热闹？
So what's Russia's big beef here, then?
就是不想让格鲁吉亚投靠西方？
They just don't want to see this place go west?
也可能是想抢这里的输油管线
It may have more to do with the oil pipeline here.
这里的油直接输向欧洲，把俄罗斯的饭碗给抢了
It goes direct to Europe which makes the Russian pipe irrelevant.
这也是在和格鲁吉亚的几个省份拔河
They're also playing tug-of-war with a couple of Georgian provinces.
-欢迎收看冷战续集！ -没错！
- Welcome to Cold War, the sequel. - Exactly!
给达奇曼打个电话？看看他们在哪儿
Wanna give Dutchman a call? See where the others are at.
好的
Yeah.
[布雷泽报道]那边
And with Wolf Blitzer,
我想您应该提一下有人在向村庄炮击
I think you should mention the shelling of the villages...
总统阁下，您的内阁成员到了
Mr President,your cabinet members are here.
-要我出去吗？ -不用，请留下
- Would you like me to go? - No. Please stay.
先生们，你们都认识克里斯，我的美国媒体顾问
Gentlemen, you all know Chris,my US press adviser.
-你好 -你好 请进
- Hello.- Yes, please come in.
-早上好 -进来 有什么事说吧
- Good morning.- Come in. Tell me news.
总统先生，最新情报显示
Mr President, the latest intelligence
独立派是在俄罗斯阵地内向我们开火的
indicates the separatists are firing from the Russian positions,
并以他们的维护部队做掩护
using their peacekeepers as shields.
说明俄罗斯是有意与他们合作
That can only mean willing cooperation.
也可能是故意要激怒我们
That could be another attempt to draw us into wider hostilities.
-就像04年那样 -我们相信这次不一样
- Just like in '04. - We believe this to be different.
俄军战机和坦克正向冲突地带开进
Russian fighter planes and tanks are moving towards the conflict zone.
黑海的一艘俄罗斯战舰也在行动
A Russian fleet in the Black Sea is also on the move.
所以你们都认为肯定要爆发战争了？
So you all believe war is certain?
我们..但愿不会
We... we pray not.
但是奥塞梯人拒绝了我们所有的外交手段
But the Ossetians, they are refusingall our efforts in diplomacy.
我们的军队处于最低战备状态
Our troops are at their lowest level of readiness.
还有几位大臣不在国内
Several ministers are also out of the country.
我们并没有应急计划
We have no contingency plan...
把他们召回来 对,召回来 各位
We'll call them back.Yes, call them back. Everyone.
不要理会这些挑衅行为 明白吗？
And I want no response yet to these provocations. Understood?
问题是在塔吉克斯坦要拿什么擦屁股？
The question is what do you wipe your arse with in Tajikistan?
那里根本没有卫生纸，哪儿都没有
There is no toilet paper anywhere.Ever.
没有报纸 没有树没有树叶 我又腹泻！
There's no newspaper, no leaves on the trees. I had the runs!
只能在草上蹭蹭了事，像一条狗
I had to slide along the grass,wipe my arse like a dog.
这画面可真美 斯蒂尔顿
That's a lovely visual, Stilton.
所以我才要喝威士忌 亲爱的
That's why I drink whisky, my dear.
它什么都能治 胃痛 甚至记忆 都能忘记
Whatever it is, tummy bugs,even memories, this kills it.
-干杯 -干杯
- Cheers.- Cheers.
哇
Whoa!
少喝点，好多会喝酒的喝这个都晕
This stuff has put more experienced drinkers than you in a coma.
不用担心他 佐伊
Don't worry about this man, Zoe.
他能把所有人都喝趴下 这个真不在话下
He can drink anyone under the table.Yours truly excepted.
你在波斯尼亚真给整惨了
You got pretty fucked up in Bosnia.
-我？才没有！-差不多吧
- Me? Never! - Most definitely.
-没有！你也去过波斯尼亚？ -我说吧？
- Never! You were in Bosnia, too?- See what I mean?
-你当时多大? 12? - 19
- What were you? 12? - 19.
穿着小花裙要做什么都容易
Everything's easier in a miniskirt.
经验之谈啊 是吧 斯蒂尔顿？
Speaking from personal experience,are you, Stilton?
嗯 波斯尼亚真是一团糟
Hmm. Bosnia's pretty fucked up.
不过不如卢旺达糟糕
Not as bad as Rwanda, though.
家家都躲在教堂里住着
Families hacked and stacked in churches.
想想要是那里有石油，人们肯定趋之若鹜
Imagine the attention that would have got if they'd had oil there.
是，战争就像个没有牙的贱女人
Yeah, war is like an old toothless whore.
达奇曼！-总的来说很恶心 不过..
- Dutchman! - Disgusting mainly. But then...
偶尔...
Every now and again...
她莫名其妙就献给了你
...she gives it to you like nobody's business.
而且是 特别奉献
I mean, special.
敬贱女人
The old whore!
哦 是的 妈咪
Oh, yes, Mommy!
-那么你们有计划了吗？-我们想和里佐联系上
- So, you guys got a... a plan yet? - We're trying to get hold of Rezo.
阿瓦利亚尼上尉 我在伊拉克的向导 你认识吗？
Captain Avaliani.You know, my guy from Iraq?
想让他给我们带带路
Thought he might have some leads.
但我们现在只知道他的部队回去了
But so far all we know is his unit's back.
嗯 根我说嘛 我在伐利亚妮认识个人
Well, let me know. I got a guy in Variani.
需要的话可以让他帮你们找个向导
He can hook you up with a guy if you need it.
-你们要去哪儿？ -茨欣瓦利
- Where you headed? - Tskhinvali.
什么？干嘛
- What? - What?
小伙子们 那里是独立派的首府啊
My dear chaps,that's the separatists' capital.
我只管扛着摄像机 跟着他走
I just go where the man tells me,and point the camera.
（我不怕高）
'I have no fear of heights
（不怕海的深）
'No fear of the deep blue sea
尽管他会使我溺死
'Although it could drown me
我知道可能溺亡
'I know it could drown me
我不会在深林中
'I didn't wander
在树木间
'In the woods
沉溺于恐慌
'Used to fear...'
好 都安排好了
OK. All set.
达曼奇的人午夜会在村广场附近和我们接头
Dutchmars guy will meet us near the village square at midnight.
哦 上帝
Oh, God!
干嘛要跑到这种鬼地方来？可能是我老了
What do they put in this shit here?Maybe I'm just getting old.
把窗户摇下来 行吗？
Roll down your window, will you?
没用 伙计 你还是停车吧
It's no good, mate.You're gonna have to pull over.
真的？
Really?
都吐出去了吗？
You all set? Lightweight.
嗯
Yeah.
事实上 我现在觉得有点饿了
Actually, I feel kind of hungry now.
-我们有零食吗？ -没有！
- Have we got any snacks? - No!
要是每隔5分钟都要停车让你下来吐
And if we have to stop every five minutes for you to puke,
我们就开不到边境了
we are never making it to the border.
去你的！
Fuck you!
-听起来像炮击 -好戏开场了
Sounds like shelling.Things are heating up.
进攻正在升级
Attacks are growing.
边境上的村庄和维护部队都遭到了袭击
Both villages and peacekeepers are under fire now.
这次有人员伤亡
We have casualties.Dead and wounded.
-我们必须还击 -我同意
- We must respond.- I agree.
还击的话，就开战了
If we respond, we are at war.
不能冒着险
We cannot risk it.
总统先生，我们的军队如果不还击
Mr President,if our troops cannot return fire,
就无法疏散伤员
they cannot evacuate the wounded.
我们要尽可能保持停火状态
We will maintain ceasefire as long as we can.
总统先生，已经可以用肉眼确认
Mr President,there is visual confirmation
俄军坦克正在集结准备发动进攻
of Russian tanks amassing for an invasion.
我今晚必须向全国和世界发表讲话
I must address country and world press tonight.
我认为这是个好注意 总统先生
I think that would be a good idea, Mr President.
-好，就这么办 -好
- OK, let's do it. - OK.
有特色的节目
There's local colour.
而且，在达奇曼的人来之前我们也有时间消遣
Besides, we've got time to kill before Dutchman's guy shows up.
你现在要改行当婚礼摄影师了？
Are you making wedding videos now?
闭嘴
Shut the fuck up.
喂！
Oi!
别看美女了 总统出来了
Stop checking out the chicks.The president's coming on.
（几小时之前，维和部队的指挥官告诉我们）
'A few hours ago, the leaders of the peacekeeping forces
（他们已经失去了）
'have told us that they have lost control
（对独立派行动的控制）
'over the actions of the separatists.
（作为回应）
'In response,
（我已经下令我军维持单方面停火状态）
'I have ordered that our side maintain a unilateral ceasefire
（以防止敌对状态升级）
'to help prevent the escalation of hostilities.'
快12点了
Nearly midnight.
达曼奇的人快来了 我去上个厕所
Dutchman's guy will be here soon.I'm gonna take a piss.
（我们急需各国领导人的协助）
'The help of the world leaders is urgently needed
（来重启和谈程序）
'to restart this peace process.'
空的存储卡
Fresh memory cards.
应该是他了 乔奇？ 我是托马斯.安德斯
That must be our guide.Giorgi? Thomas Anders.
-嗨 -你好
- Hi. - Hello.
我们得把车藏在边界至少半英里之外
We have to hide the car at least half a mile from the border.
许多部队正在开进 路要被封了
A lot of troops are on the move,and roads are being closed.
你们挑了个穿越缓冲地带的好时机
You picked a good night to cross through the buffer zone.
名天可能就过不去了
It may not be possible tomorrow.
-你能带我们去茨欣瓦利？ -是的 非常近 但是..
- You can get us to Tskhinvali? - Yes, very close. But...
那些是苏霍伊战斗机 带着炸弹！
Those are Sukhois.On a bomb run!
嘿！各位！
Hey! Everybody!
大家找掩护！快进去！
Everybody get under cover!Get inside now!
-你还好吗？ -还好 你流了好多血
- Are you OK? OK? - I'm OK. You're bleeding really bad.
-塞波延 你还好吗？ -还好
- Sebastian, are you OK? - Yeah.
-你叫什么？ -塔蒂亚
- What's your name? - Tatia.
塔蒂亚，我是安德斯 能帮我一下吗？
Tatia, I'm Anders. Can you help me, please?
握紧
Hold it up.
帮我把这个撕下来当绷带 行吗？
I need you to rip a piece of this for a bandage, OK?
索夫！那是我姐姐！
Sofi! That's my sister!
好 去吧 去吧
All right. You go, you go.
先生！喂！过来下！你需要握住这个
Sir! Whoa! Come here! You need to hold this up.
塔蒂亚！塔蒂亚！
Tatia! Tatia!
塔蒂亚！塔蒂亚！听我说
Tatia, Tatia, listen to me.
再给我块桌布 我需要绷带 好吗？
Get me another piece of tablecloth.I need another bandage, OK?
我们得带伤员离开这里
We have to get the wounded out of here.
好 坐在我后面 握住他的手
Good. Now sit behind me. Hold her hand.
告诉她会好起来的 我们会带她去医院的
Tell her she's gonna be OK.We're gonna get her to a hospital.
我要送这一男一女去医院
I need to get this woman and that man to a hospital,
否则他们会有生命危险
or they're not gonna make it.
最近的医院在哥里市
The nearest hospital in Gori.
-她受了惊吓 她希望我一起去 -好的
- She's scared. She wants me to come.- All right.
你知道怎么去哥里吗？好 其余人多保重
You know the way to Gori? Good. You guys, careful now.
轻一点 小心
Careful with her. Careful.
-你是美国人？ -不 我只是在那儿学习
- Are you American? - No. I just studied there.
下个十字路口左转
Turn left at the next intersection.
该死的！
No fucking way!
不不不！我们是记者！
No, no, no! Press!
-好好看看！ -记者！-记者！
- Use your eyes! - Press! Press!
我们有人受伤了 求你了 让我们过去吧
We got wounded people here.Come on. Let us through.
好吗？好吗？
OK? OK?
好非常感谢
OK. Thank you very much!
你父亲和姐姐会没事的 他们在我们后面
Your father and sister will be OK.They're behind us.
我身后是哥里市军医院
This is the scene outside the Gori Military Hospital,
目前这是该地区唯一诊治
the only one in the area where wounded soldiers and civilians
昨晚炮击中受伤的军人和平民的地方
injured in last night's shelling are all being treated.
（至于这次激烈对抗的原因，各方仍是争议不断）
'The reasons for this outbreak of heavy fighting remain hotly disputed,
（俄方声称格鲁吉亚无端挑起攻击）
'with Russia claiming the Georgians attacked unprovoked.
（而第比利斯政府则称他们的部队）
'Whereas the government in Tbilisi claims their troops...'
（攻击的坦克属于非法进入格鲁吉亚领地）
...fired at Russian tanks entering illegally into Georgian territory.
格鲁吉亚的主权
Sovereign Georgia.
双方关于此次交火升级
Both sides have a dramatically...
持有截然不同的论调
...different account of this escalation.
我是托马斯.安德斯，在格鲁吉亚
This is Thomas Anders, reporting in Geor...
我是托马斯.安德斯 在格鲁吉亚哥里市发回的报道
This is Thomas Anders reporting in Gori, Georgia.
很好
OK.
不错，凭这个我们都能上美国有线新闻网了
Well, that might get us on CNN.
我们要大显身手了 我要打电话给制作人
We can rock and roll that. I'm gonna call our producer.
（我是迈克.斯蒂尔顿 在格鲁吉亚哥里市为您报道）
'This is Michael Stilton reporting from Gori, Georgia.'
真不错 我得喝点水
Very gory it is, too. I need a drink.
卡林
Karin?
纽约独立新闻中心 2008年8月8日
Independent News Center New York August 8, 2008
-我听不见你 -我说没希望了 抱歉
- 'I can't hear you.' - No bites. I'm sorry.
新闻都在播奥运会
The networks are all covering the Olympics.
今天是开幕式
The opening ceremony started today.
你有提过这里爆发战争了吗？
Did you mention a war started here?
当然 可大家只相信克里姆林宫的论断
'Of course. But everyone's taking the Kremlin line.'
梅德韦杰夫说是格鲁吉亚先开火的
Medvedev is saying the Georgians fired first,
他们的部队只是在保护公民而已
and their troops are just protecting their citizens.
（然后 98%住在南奥塞梯的人）
'Apparently, 98 % of the people in South Ossetia
（一夜之间就都成了俄罗斯公民）
'suddenly have Russian passports.'
被轰炸的村落离冲突地带还有好几英里
Protecting them by cluster-bombing villages
他们就这么保护公民啊！
miles outside the conflict zone!
我知道 安德斯 我支持你 可你知道这些人
I know, Anders. I'm on your side.You know what these people are like.
他们根本来不及报道这场战争
They barely find the time to cover the war we're in.
你需要..等等
You need to just... Hold on.
普京正在北京接受采访
Putin's on from Beijing.
（一切公开透明）
'There is no secret about it.
（我们已考虑各种情况）
'We had considered all scenarios,
（包括来自格鲁吉亚政府的直接挑衅）
'including direct aggression by the Georgian leadership.
（我们必须事先考虑清楚）
'We had to think beforehand about how to provide
（如何保护维和部队以及俄罗斯公民）
'for the security of our peacekeepers and of Russian citizens
（即南奥塞梯居民的安全）
'who are residents of South Ossetia.
（我们愿与周边睦邻及所有盟国合作）
'We want to cooperate with all our neighbours, with all of our partners.
（如果任何人认为可以侵犯我们）
'If anyone thinks they can come and kill us,
（认为我们的土地已丧失生机）
'that our place is at the cemetery,
（他们必须想清楚这将会有什么后果）
'they should think what consequences such a policy will have for them.'
怎么样？
What?
我倒好奇接下来会怎么样！
I said I wonder what that will look like!
-是的 -（等下 这就完了）
- Yeah. - 'Wait. That's it?'
那格鲁吉亚呢？没人有疑问吗？
Where's the Georgian side? No questions even?
真难以置信！卡林？
Fucking unbelievable! Karin?
新闻想要更平民化的报道？
The networks want something more personal?
嘿！塔蒂亚！嘿！大家都还好吗？
Hey, Tatia! Hey, hey! Everyone make it out OK?
我联系不上索夫和我爸爸
I can't reach Sofi or my father.
电话在伐利亚用不了
The phones are not working in Variani.
-听着 -我觉得 -嘿
- Look, I mean... - Hey.
你得休息下 来吧 到外面透透气
I think you need to take five.Come on. Let's get some air.
谢谢你
Thank you.
-那么，你在美国念过书？ -是的
- So, you studied in the States? - Yeah.
哪里？
Where?
纽约 政治学
New York. Political science.
曾经想过留在那，但还是回来教书了
Thought about staying,but came back here to teach.
这是什么？现场采访？
What is this? An interview now?
好吧
OK.
美军现在在哪儿？
Where's the US?
打伊拉克的时候我们派了部队,现在你们却躲起来了
We were there for you with Iraq,and you're nowhere to be seen.
不..我不同意你的看法
No. I... I agree with you.
军队封路之前我姨妈和我姨夫侥幸逃脱了
My aunt and her husband got out OK before the army closed the roads.
她说其他人都去了附近的村庄避难，所以..
She said everybody else had to go to nearby villages for shelter, so...
我得回去找他们
I gotta get back up there.
-我们也要回北方 -真的？
- We're going back north.- Really?
谢谢你们请客
Thanks for the offer.
我要去找我姨妈和我表姐
I'm gonna go to my cousirs and see my aunt.
以后电话联系我们
Call us later.
安德斯 怎么了
Anders,What the hell was that?
我说真的 伙计 下次先问问我可以吗？
Seriously, man, you mind fucking consulting me next time?
我不希望他回北方 为了她好
I don't want her coming north.For her own good.
我们需要她 她也需要我们
We need her. She needs us.
这正是新闻界需要的故事
This is exactly the kind of story the networks care about.
离散的家人 相逢重聚
Missing family, reunion.
我不想一路上保护人
I don't want someone along I gotta protect.
怎么 你现在要树立良好声誉了？
What, you believe in your own reputation now?
为什么？因为玛丽安？乔奇？
Why? Because of Miriam? Giorgi?
嘿 我跟你讲
Hey, check out this living hotness.
我看你就是人身保险的最佳承保对象
You've been the best life insurance policy I ever got.
你同样是个疯狂的家伙 但每次都能平安而返
You are also a crazy motherfucker,but we always come out OK.
这就是我要的
And that's the way I like it.
I don't want complications and entanglements.
塔蒂亚不是玛丽安
Tatia is not Miriam.
安德斯 你得放下她了
Anders, you've gotta let that go.
我们来是为报道战争的
We came here to cover a war.
如果我们没有故事 就永远没人知道这一切
If we don't get a story,this will all unfold unseen.
对吗？好的
Yeah? OK.
你觉得这有用吗？
You really think this is gonna work?
这点事对她来说小菜一碟
I've seen her work bigger miracles.
谢谢你 这样好吗？
Thank you. You know what?
我把我的电话留给你 好吗？
I'm going to write you down my numbers, OK?
谢谢 再会了
Thank you. See you guys.
那么 伙计们 任务完成
So, guys, mission accomplished.
他会和阿瓦利亚尼的部队取得联系
He's gonna get in touch with Avaliani's unit.
他们正要往那边走
They're headed this way.
你们可以和他们一同前去 之后离目的地也不远了
You're gonna need to ride with them,or you won't get far.
主要道路仍在封锁中 每隔1英里左右就有检查点
The main roads are still shut down.Checkpoints every single mile or so.
你太让人惊讶了
You're amazing!
你知道他们说的什么 穿着小花裙要做什么都容易
You know what they say.Everything's easier in a miniskirt.
听说昨晚你们逃过一劫持 对不起
Heard you guys had a rough night last night. Sorry.
你去哪里了？
Where did you end up?
斯蒂尔顿派我去首都搞一些..政府之类的
Stilton sent me to the capital to get some... government shit.
我刚走20秒，俄军就轰炸了
20 seconds away from the Russians
这以外20公里的那条机场跑道
bombing an airstrip 20 clicks from here.
有时候那没牙的贱女人还真有点..
Sometimes that toothless whore is...
无情
...unkind.
给我现金
Give me the cash!
我叫塞柏延.甘兹
My name's Sebastian Ganz.
我要找里佐.阿瓦利亚尼上尉
I'm trying to get a hold of Captain Rezo Avaliani.
高居于山 娱乐至死
Up in the mountains. Entertain us all.
就像一个疯狂的圣诞老人
Like a crazy sexy Santa Claus.
听着 我只想说谢谢你们带我回到北边
Listen, I just wanted to say thank you for taking me up north.
还有对之前跟你发脾气表示歉意
And I'm sorry I snapped at you earlier.
全是因为这些..真的很冷酷
It's just this is all... really hard.
索芙的婚礼本可以给我们所有人一个新的开始
Sofi's wedding was supposed to be a new beginning for all of us.
你什么意思？
What do you mean?
我爸爸和我一直相处得不太好
My father and I have never really gotten along,
我去美国读书也是其中的原因之一
and my going to America was just one of many things.
他的祖籍是奥塞梯
His side of the family is Ossetian,
我们在政治上..有太多的冲突
and we've had...more fights about politics
多得我都记不清了
than I care to remember.
不 听着 我们要去伐利亚尼
No, listen, we're trying to get to Variani,
我想也许我们有幸可以搭你们的车
and we wondered if we might be able to hitch a ride along with you guys.
我们有好几年没说过话了
We haven't spoken to each other in years.
你的家人怎么样？他们肯定很担心你
How about your family? They must be worried sick.
不，不会，我没有家人
No, no. I don't have one.
对不起
Sorry.
好了 终于和阿瓦利亚联系上了
OK. Finally connected with Avaliani.
他的车队会在拂晓时经过这里
His convoy will pass here at first light,
我们可以先搭他们的车 等离伐利亚尼1英里的时候
and we can ride with them to about a mile from Variani.
再下车自己想办法过去
But then we're on our own.
太好了 谢谢你 你们大家
Great. Thank you. Both of you.
嘿 伙计们！总统回来了！
Hey, guys! The president's back on!
（我的公民们 各国领导们）
'My fellow citizens and world leaders.
（我们正在遭受俄罗斯军队的大规模进攻）
'We are facing a massive attack by Russian forces
他们现在控制了茨欣瓦利
'who now control Tskhinvali.
（我们不得不呼吁我们西方的所有朋友）
'We have called out to all our friends in the West,
（相信你们不会纵容这场侵略继续下去）
'and trust that you will not allow this aggression to continue.
（我已经命令我们的武装部队阻止任何军用车辆）
'I have directed our Armed Forces to prevent all military vehicles
（进入格鲁吉亚的国土）
'from entering Georgian territory,
（并阻止任何对我们的攻击）
'and to suppress any position attacking us.
（我在此宣布全民动员令）
'I hereby decree that a universal mobilisation
（即刻生效）
'is now in effect,
（所有预备役军官必须立即报到）
'and all reserve officers must report in.
（愿上帝保佑格鲁吉亚和我们所有的人）
'May God save Georgia and all of us.'
坐
Sit down.
-你认为世界会听得到吗？ -但愿如此
- Think the world heard me? - I hope so.
但愿如此？
You hope so?
美国呢？助理国务卿布雷扎怎么说？
The Americans? Bryza at the State Department?
布什总统已经非常明确地表示他们不会干涉 也不能
Mr Bush has make it very clear that they will not intervene. Can't.
至少在军事方面
Not militarily, anyway.
那正是俄罗斯人希望的
That's just what the Russians want.
美国人肯定知道我别无选择
The Americans must know that I had no choice.
如果我无动于衷 俄罗斯人肯定早就闯进来了
If I'd stood by, the Russians would be here by now,
我们会失去整个国家！另一个车臣共和国！
and my whole country would be lost! Another Chechenya!
如果美国人不帮忙 欧洲必须帮助我们！
If the Americans won't help,then Europe must come to our aid!
不管是谁 谁都可以
But someone. Someone has to come.
事情变得棘手了 总统先生
That's gonna be tough, Mr President.
梅德韦杰夫称这是俄罗斯的“9.11”事件
Medvedev is already playing this as a Russian 9/11.
哦！拜托！哦！
Oh, please! Oh!
他在新闻发布会上指责你的士兵
He's having press conferences accusing your soldiers
打死了茨欣瓦利的无辜平民
of killing innocent civilians in Tskhinvali.
-他管这个叫科索沃！ -真是令人发指！
- He's calling this Kosovo! - But it's outrageous!
我们尽了一切所能来减少平民伤亡
We did everything we could to minimise civilian casualties
但我们也要保卫自己！
while defending ourselves!
这次我们争取别再把车弄坏了 好吗？
Let's try and keep this car in one piece, eh?
不然赫尔兹这辈子就不会再租给我任何东西了
Otherwise Hertz will never rent me anything ever again.
很高兴见到你 我的朋友
It's good to see you, my friend.
我也是 里佐 本以为重逢的光景能好些
You, too, Rezo. I wish it were under better circumstances.
-赛巴斯蒂安全都解释过了？ -是的
- Sebastian explained everything? - Yes.
-你介意我们拍摄吗？ -不
- Do you mind if we film? - No.
好了
OK.
上尉，这是塔蒂亚 她和家人失散了
Captain, this is Tatia, whose family is missing.
谢谢你们的护送
Thanks for the escort.
是的 我希望他们安全
Yeah, I hope they are safe.
安德斯 你和我们一辆车
Anders, you ride with us.
赛巴斯蒂安 你会在后面跟着
Sebastian, you will follow.
那么 前线的情况如何？
So, what's the situation at the front?
我们的情报显示来的不止是俄罗斯人
Our intelligence indicates that not only the Russians are coming,
还有志愿兵和雇佣军
but volunteer militia and mercenaries
来帮助俄军扫荡村庄
to help the Russianscleanse the villages.
如果你看到带白袖章和黑面具的人
You see men with white armbands and black masks,
千万别拍他们
you don't take pictures.
也不要去躲 快跑
You don't try to hide. You run.
明白了吗？
Understand?
你的朋友 安德斯 人很酷
Your friend, Anders, is pretty cold.
听着 他不是有意的
Listen, he doesn't mean it.
他和人交流有点困难
He just has a hard time relating to people.
你知道吗 他有过一些痛苦的经历
You know, he's been through some really bad shit.
之前在伊拉克
Iraq and before.
但他是一个好人
But he's a good guy.
他很关心你还有你的家人
He cares about you and your family.
他只是想保证你的安全
He just wants to keep you safe.
-那是什么？ -意思是“天意”
- What's that? - It means "God willing".
对！说的不错！
Yes! That's good!
确实
That's nice.
你知道 里佐 真的很感谢你 但是
You know, Rezo, thank you so much for this, but...
我想我还是把这个还给你吧
...I think I should give it back to you.
不 我是特意给你的
No. I give to you for reason.
你知道圣乔治的故事吗？
Do you know the story of St George?
嗯..士兵的守护神
Uh... the patron saint of soldiers.
是的 他的模样遍布所有的教堂
Yes. His image is in all churches.
他曾是一个罗马士兵
He was a Roman soldier
由于拒绝放弃真相而被杀害
martyred for refusing to abandon the truth.
你们将伊拉克的真相公布于众
You were trying to tell the truth in Iraq.
我们只能送你们到这儿了 上帝与你们同在 我的朋友
This is as far as we can take you.God be with you, my friend.
谢谢你
Thank you.
不知道？
No?
这已经是第5个村子了 我们怎么才能找到他们？
This is the fifth village.How are we supposed to find them?
她说什么？
What's she saying?
她认为可以帮助我们 她要看看照片
She thinks she can help us.She wants to see the pictures.
她们说什么？他们说什么？
What are they saying? What did they say?
她说她表亲在艾奈维开了家小旅馆 离这儿5公里
Her cousin owns an inn in Avnevi,5km from here,
不久前有个新娘去了那里避难
and he took in a bride seeking shelter.
新娘和她父亲
A bride and her father.
我们来检查一下入住登记
Let's check the registration.
索芙！
Sofi!
嘿
Hey.
-他在说什么？ -战斗机！战斗机！
- What's he saying? - Jets! Jets!
各位 快找个地方躲起来 现在！
Guys, we need to get to a shelter. Now!
我们这下面没准备多少吃的
We do not have much down here,
不过你们尽管吃吧
but you are welcome to have it.
你们一定饿了
You must be hungry.
俄军坦克已闯入格鲁吉亚的非争议地区
Russian tanks are crossing into undisputed Georgian territory.
全国范围内的机场都遭到了空袭
The air force is bombing airfields all across the country.
有战舰封锁了我们的港口
Battleships are moving in to block our ports.
-我的上帝 -我们今天早上出发的时候
- My God. - We leave at first light.
阿瓦利亚尼告诉我除了俄军还有志愿兵
Avaliani told me volunteer militia are coming with the Russians.
我们应该先休息一下
We should try to get some rest.
赛巴斯蒂安?赛巴斯蒂安,醒醒!快!我们得走了!来吧!
Sebastian? Sebastian, wake up! Quickly! We've gotta go! Come on!
不行了,有直升机.塔蒂亚,找地方躲起来!
We can't. There's choppers.Tatia, hiding places!
这边有座桥!
Bridge over this way!
-我们得走另一条路! -我们要拍下这个
- We have to go another way! - We have to see this.
过来.这边.过河.过来
Come on. This way. The river. Come on.
无论发生什么都不要出声!
Not a sound! No matter what happens.
他在说什么?
What did he say?
他说他要见警长和市长
He said he wants the chief of police and the mayor.
不！我们应该做点什么！
No! We have to do something!
在这儿我们什么都做不了
There's nothing we can do.
他们会把我们全都杀了的!
They'll kill us all!
天啊!
Jesus!
我们快她妈离开这儿吧,赛巴斯蒂安
Let's get the fuck out of here, Sebastian.
再等一下
Just one sec.
把他们都干掉!
Clear them out!
该死！我们走！-我们走！走！
- Shit! Let's go!- Let's go! Go!
(米-24"雌鹿"武装直升机)
我的上帝！怎么会这样!
My God! This can't be happening!
嘘!安静!安静!
Shh! Stay calm! Stay calm!
所有人,都进来,塔蒂亚,让大家都躲起来
Everybody, in here. Tatia, hide everybody.
好!我们会找到出去的路!过来！快快！
-OK! - We'll find a way out! Come on! Quick! Quick!
嘘!嘘!
Shh, shh!
求你同情一下吧
Please have pity.
看在上帝的份上
In the name of God.
嘘
Shh.
这里没人了
It's all clear.
你个白痴!
You idiot!
如果不出来我们就把你们全打死
Come out or we'll kill you all!
停下,停下!好了!停下!
Stop, stop, stop! All right, stop!
记者 记者！
Press, press!
别开枪！不要开枪！
Don't shoot! Don't shoot!
我们是奥塞梯人!
We're Ossetian!
我们是朋友
We are friends!
-不要！-别碰她 你这混蛋！
- Don't! - Don't touch her, you fuck!
好了 好了！
OK, OK!
这些都是他们的东西
This is all they had on them.
我们还在车上找到了第二个摄像机
We found a second camera in the car.
你们在格鲁吉亚做什么,安德斯和甘兹先生/
What are you doing in Avnevi,Mr Anders and Mr Ganz?
战斗打响的时候
We were filming in a neighbouring village
我们正在临近的一个村子拍摄
when the fighting broke out.
拍摄她的婚礼
Filming her wedding.
你们战地记者会对格鲁吉亚的婚礼感兴趣吗？
And are Georgian weddings a common passion for war reporters?
真让人惊讶，谷歌一下能找到这么多信息
This is amazing,what a simple Google search can find.
看，你们是托马斯.安德斯和赛巴斯蒂安.甘兹
Look. You are Thomas Andersand Sebastian Ganz.
在去萨马的路上遭到了什叶派武装分子的袭击
Ambushed by Shiite militants on the road to Samarra.
玛丽安.艾斯纳 美国记者,不幸遇难
Miriam Eisner, American reporter,was killed.
这个存储卡是加密的.请把密码告诉我
The memory card is security coded.Give me the code, please.
7-6-7-6
-不错的婚礼. -嗯
- Nice wedding. - Mm-hm.
我去和那女人谈谈
I can make the women talk.
你不准碰我的女儿！
You will not touch my daughters!
他们和我一样是奥塞梯人
They are Ossetians like me.
我们喜欢你
We are like you.
我是哥萨克人，老头
I am a Cossack, old man.
下次你再冲我大喊大叫
And the next time you raise your voice at me,
我就在你女儿面前砍死你
I will cut you open while your daughters watch.
丹尼尔，丹尼尔..
Daniil. Daniil...
先把这位父亲带走
Take the father first.
不,你不能这样做！
No, you can't do this!
如果这里面有录像,我们就要找到它
If there is a video recording,we have to find it.
我们不需要像美国在伊拉克的那种恶梦
We don't need a PR nightmare like the Americans in Iraq.
不用担心,我们会找到的
Don't worry, we'll find it.
长官,我们刚收到消息已发动第二轮进攻
Sir, we just received word that the second invasion front has launched.
好
Good.
总统先生,我们的两个战线正面临着大规模的进攻
Mr President, we now face a massive assault on two fronts.
我们估计俄军的规模为4万人
We estimate the total size of the Russian force at 40,000 men.
超过了我们军队的3倍
More than three times than our own army.
-他们还能坚持多长时间？ -我们无法在两条战线作战
- How long can they hold? - We cannot fight a two-front war.
我们在阿布哈兹的军队必须撤退，否则会被全部歼灭
Our troops in Abkhazia must retreat,or they will be wiped out.
让他们撤出阵地
Pull them back.
有什么新闻吗,克里斯托弗？
What's the news, Christopher?
美国对于我们停火的提议新闻上怎么说？
Any news from the Americanson our ceasefire proposal?
布什总统亲自与梅德韦杰夫和普京通话
I was told that President Bush spoke to Medvedev and Putin personally.
他们并不感兴趣
They're not interested.
普京昨天离开北京后说过他会亲自处理这件事
Putin left Beijing yesterday and said he would command this personally.
他跟萨科奇说除非我下台否则他不会放弃
He told Sarkozy he would not quit until I am hanged by my balls!
这里有些好消息
There is some good news.
欧盟部长已经同意召开紧急会议
The EU ministers have agreed to an emergency meeting.
哦,谢谢你,欧盟 紧急会议!哦！
Oh, thank you, EU An emergency meeting! Oh!
哦,我们来些鸡尾酒吧!香槟!我们来庆祝一下
Oh, let's bring cocktails! Champagne! Let's celebrate
会议,更多的会议!再多些会议,别再开会了!
Meetings. More meetings! And more meetings. No more meetings!
有些人总是在坐着开会,而我们的人却在一个个倒下！
Every time some people sit in meetings, more of our people die!
欧盟的代表必须到这里来！
The EU representatives have to come here!
他们得和我们站在一起！
They have to stand with us!
你把真的存储卡怎样了？
What did you do with the real card?
那个人打你的时候掉在地上了
It's in the ground where you fell after that guy hit you.
我过去扶你的时候顺手把它埋起来了
I buried it when I came over to help you.
在果园的时候我调换了两张存储卡.我们得把录像播出去
I swapped the cards in the orchard. We have to get that footage out.
爸爸,你还好吗？他们伤害你了吗？
Papa, are you alright? Did they hurt you?
我很好 我很好
I'm alright, I'm alright.
嘿！安德斯
Hey! Anders!
嘿,你们要把他带哪儿去？赛巴斯蒂安！
Hey, where are you taking him? Sebastian!
漂亮的教堂
Beautiful church.
你知道在格鲁吉亚有几座世界上最古老的教堂吗？
Do you know that Georgia has some of the oldest churches in the world?
至少他们能在战火中幸存下来
At least they will be left when this is over.
我莫斯科的领袖们也不想冒这个险
My leaders in Moscow have decided they don't want to risk
因这次行动而受到教会谴责
the church's condemnation of this project.
你玩吗？
Do you play?
用英语说
In English.
你确定他们没有伤害你吗？
Are you sure they didn't hurt you?
是,是啊
Yes, yes.
那么他们对你做了什么了 你去了那么长时间
So, what did they do to you? You were gone a long time.
你什么都没有告诉他们吗？
You didn't tell them anything, did you?
哦,天啊！
Oh, Christ!
这棋盘式我儿子送给我的礼物 萨沙 他在阿富汗阵亡了
This board was a gift from my son,Sasha. He died in Afghanistan.
不错啊 安德斯先生 不错
Not bad, Mr Anders. Not bad.
我的死时只有21岁
My Sasha was only 21 when he was killed.
他被敌军士兵捉住了
He was captured by enemy soldiers.
你能想象得到他们对他做了什么
You can imagine the things they did to him.
这并不能成为你在这里胡作非为的借口
That doesn't excuse what you did here.
当然不能
Of course it doesn't.
我只是这样说..你知道我是明白的
I just say so...you know I understand.
明白什么？
Understand what?
你的眼神
That look in your eyes.
失去家人之后的那种空洞
The emptiness that comes from burying your family.
你失去了你的父母 交通事故 是吗？
You lost your parents. Car accident, wasn't it?
酒后驾车 迎面相撞
Drunk driver. Head-on collision.
你知道有意思的是什么吗？
You know what is interesting?
家人死后我们都开始追寻战争
That we both asked for combat after family death.
如果有人问我们
And if people asked us,
我确定我们能给出很多我们这样做的原因
I'm sure we'd give them many reasons for why we did it.
但如果我们直言不讳
But if we are honest...
我认为我们只是在追寻声音
...I think we just sought noise,
来淹没其他的思想
to drown out all other thoughts.
去忘记
To forget.
片刻之后 在那声音中
Then after a while, in that noise,
你开始感到自己免疫了
you start to feel... immune.
我是正确的吗？
Am I right?
不幸的是 这样的态度使人倾向于冒险
Unfortunately, such an attitude makes one prone to taking risks.
有时真的无所顾忌
Really careless sometimes.
就像接受一个什叶派牧师的
Like accepting a Shiite cleric's invitation
采访邀请 直接驶向死亡的陷阱
for an interview,driving straight into a deadly trap.
-闭上你的嘴 -什么？
- You shut your mouth.- What?
你觉得自己的隐私受到侵犯了?
You feel your privacy has been invaded?
但是那不正是你在做的吗？
But isn't that what you do?
捕捉人最脆弱的一面？
Capture people at their most vulnerable?
够了！
Enough!
俄罗斯雇佣了我们 因为他们自己的军队没有积极性
Russia hires us, because their own army is not motivated.
他们开价很高 让我们去做..特殊工作
They pay us well for... special jobs.
比如,我们有时会抓捕逃亡者
Like, we catch deserters sometimes.
幸运的人会被审问
The lucky ones would get trial.
但是最坏的人
But the worst men...
他们会交给我
...they give to me.
你怎么能告诉他们呢？
How could you have told them?
他们现在会杀了他们的！还有我们！
They will kill them now! All of us!
他们早就知道一切了
They already know everything.
录像在哪里？告诉我！
Where is the recording? Tell me!
我不知道!
I don't know!
塔蒂亚,不要跟我耍花样!
Tatia, do not play games with me!
这些人可能是奥塞梯人
These men may be Ossetians,
但他们不会永远等下去的
but they will not wait forever.
告诉我存储卡的位置
Tell me the location of the memory card,
我就放你们大家走
and I will let you all go.
我可以保证
You have my word.
我不知道你在说什么
I don't know what you're talking about.
我们别那么做了
Let's not do that.
你的朋友可没这么好受
Your friend doesn't have that kind of time.
你们对他做了什么？
What are you doing to him?
我可以开始了吗,少校？
May I begin, Colonel?
等一下
Hold on.
我们现在必须为自己考虑了
We must think of ourselves now.
而不是两个陌生人！
Not two strangers!
你认为他们不会离开我们？他们会像这个世界一样抛弃我们
You think they wouldn't leave us? They will abandon us like the world has!
塔蒂亚,告诉我录像在哪儿？
Tatia, tell me where the recording is?
你们美国人！
You Americans!
萨卡什维利发动了这场战争！
Saakashvili started this war!
你明白吗？
You understand?
我们在这儿只是为了保护我们在南奥塞梯的人！
We are here just to protect our people in South Ossetia!
我他妈才不管你想要保护谁！
I can't give a fuck who you think you're trying to protect!
但是我想知道是什么让你去射杀一个妇女的
But I would love to know how shooting an old woman helps you to do it.
我只是一名士兵,我有我的使命
I'm only a soldier.I have my orders.
格鲁吉亚已经输掉了这场战争
Georgia already lost this war.
-你不听我的 -你怎么..？
- You didn't listen to me.- How the hell did you...?
我们正在撤退.随后听说这里被袭击了
We had to fall back.Then we heard the attack here.
-他们抓住了赛巴斯蒂安 -好的 我们会解决
- They got Sebastian.- Yes. We are on it.
他们抓住了塔蒂亚和她的家人
And they got Tatia and her family.
-哪条路？ -在地下室的牢房
- Which way? - The jail in the basement.
-你还好吗,伙计? -是的
- Are you all right, bucko? - Yeah.
还好？
Yeah?
我们可用他们做盾牌！
We can use them as shields!
钥匙！
Keys!
你回来了！
You came back!
-是啊 你受伤了吗？ -没有
- Yeah. You hurt? - No.
好的 我们走
OK. Let's go.
塔蒂亚！
Tatia!
不,我不能相信你
No, I can't trust you.
塔蒂亚，我是你爸爸...
Tatia, I'm your father...
他们需要我的帮助
They need my help.
不,你和你的朋友在一起更安全
No. You'll be safer with your friends.
医生！
Medic!
-你还好吗？-没事..只是我的胳膊
- Are you okay? - It's nothing... just my arm.
我说医生！
Medic I said!
抓住他们！
Get them!
你紧跟着我
You stay close to me.
发动车辆！
Get the vehicles started!
我们得找到存储卡
We need to get the memory card!
我知道！
I know!
掩护我们！
Cover us!
过来！进去！
Come on! Get in!
进去！快！
Get in! Quickly!
坦克来了 上尉！
Tank coming, Captain!
-上尉！-我知道！
- Captain!- I know!
低下头！
Stay down!
我得下去！我们有战争罪的证据！
I have to get out! We have evidence of a war crime!
在果园周围的那条路上见！
Meet you where the road comes around the orchard!
真是个疯子
That guy's crazy.
（LAW单兵火箭筒）
减速！慢点！
Slow down! Slow down!
来吧！来吧！
Come on! Come on!
你拿到存储卡了吗？ -是的
- Did you get the memory card? - Yeah.
-你还好吗？-是的，我很好
- Are you all right? - Yeah, I'm fine.
我们快出去了
We're almost out.
爸爸！
Papa!
趴下！
Get down!
梅德韦杰夫拒绝了新的和平提议
Medvedev has refused new peace proposals.
哪部分？
Which parts?
所有的
All of them.
他告诉萨科奇说他们有自己的需要
He told Sarkozy that they have their own demands.
-什么需要？ -他们明天要把他们送出去
- What possible demands? - They're sending them over tomorrow.
我要宣布单方面停火
I am reinstating unilateral ceasefire.
-总统先生...-我们所有的军队 停火
- Mr President... - All our troops, ceasefire.
撤退到第比利斯.我们必须保卫我们的首都
Fall back to Tbilisi.We must defend our capital.
如果外界对我们的姿态没有任何回应,这就是自杀！
If the world does not respond to this gesture, it is suicide!
这是我们幸存的唯一选择
It is the only chance we have for survival.
我们应该在中午之前到达哥里
We should reach Gori by noon.
它是最近的有广播中心的城市
It is the nearest city with broadcast centre.
那里还有更快的路线吗？我们现在得把录像播出去
Isn't there a faster route? We need to get this footage out now.
没有 我们必须离开公路
No. We must stay off road.
我对你失去的表示抱歉
I'm... sorry for your loss.
我不是冒犯.这..
I don't mean to offend. It's...
只是在我的生命中已经失去了太多的人
It's just I've lost many people in my life.
但是我相信我们面对的所有磨难..
But I believe that all the trials that we face...
都是在指引我们达到目的
...lead us to our purpose.
谢谢你
Thank you.
你相信什么 安德斯？
What do you believe, Anders?
我不知道
I don't know.
你们放弃了自己的岗位？
You're abandoning your post?
是总统的命令
By order of the President.
撤回所有军队
All troops are to fall back
保卫第比利斯
and report to defend Tbilisi.
哥里市要沦陷了
Gori is going to fall.
我很抱歉.我有我的命令
I'm sorry. I have my orders.
他在说什么？
What did he say?
-他们要抛弃城市 -我们正要去那儿！
- They're abandoning the city. - We've got to get in there!
-你打算怎么办？ -我不会逃走
- What do you wanna do? - I will not run.
我不会抛下我的祖国！
I will not lose my country!
为了格鲁吉亚的自由我战斗的太多了
I've fought in too many wars to keep Georgia free.
-哪条路是去广播中心的？-那条！东边！
- Which way to the broadcast centre? - That way! East!
我很抱歉 我们必须把你们留在这儿了
I'm sorry. We must leave you here.
我得尝试建立防御 你们必须尽最大努力离开城市
I need to attempt a defence. As soon as you can, you must leave the city.
这里会变得非常危险
It will become very dangerous.
-多保重,里佐 -上帝与你同在-
- Take care, Rezo. - God be with you.
-你拿着存储卡呢吗？ -是的
- You got the card? - Yeah.
首先,我们需要找一个愿意播放录像的网络
First, we need an upload code
并得到它的上传代码
from a network willing to accept the footage.
该死！他们都走了！
Shit! They've gone!
-我们现在该做些什么？ -我们需要一部电话
- What do we do now? - We need a phone.
-（国际接线员）-接一个通美国的付费电话
- 'International operator.' - A collect call to the USA.
我得吃点东西
I need to eat something.
嘿！我找到水了！
Hey! I got water!
-嘿,卡琳  -感谢上帝！
- Hey, Karin. - 'Thank God!'
-你们还好吗？ -是的 我们在哥里
- You guys all right? - 'Yeah. We're in Gori.'
哥里？那里被轰炸了！
Gori? It's been bombed!
-我知道 -你得离开
- I know. - 'You need to get out.'
找到硬币了！
Got coins!
不 我们有一些东西需要上传,我需要一个网络！
No. We have something we need to upload. I need a network!
-俄军可能会攻占.. -卡琳,我知道!听我说！
- The Russians are likely to take... - 'Karin, I know! Listen to me!'
我们亲眼目睹了一些事.杀戮.在一个村庄的处决
We witnessed something. Killings. Executions in a village.
赛巴斯蒂安全都录下来了.我们得把它播出来.
Sebastian got it all on tape. We have to get it out.
-（现在） -是的,但是怎么办？
- 'Now.' - Yeah, but how?
这里的媒体中心支持卫星上传
There's a media centre building here with a satellite upload capability.
我们能进去,但我们需要一个愿意
We can get in,but we need for a network
帮我们播放的网络..一个接入码
to accept the feed and give us... an access code.
她最好快点!空袭就要来了
She'd better hurry! The bombing's winding down.
也就是地面部队已经做好准备了
Which means the ground troops are getting ready.
-你听到了吗？ -是的,但是安德斯..
- You hear that? - 'Yeah, but Anders...'
我已经跟大家说了.没有人在乎
I have already tried everyone.No one cares.
（但我会再试试罗杰.麦提尔尼.如果有人能办到,就是他了）
'But I'll try Roger McTierney.If anyone can get it on, it's him.'
好,好,好的
Yeah, yeah. OK.
给
Here.
给我那些硬币,我们找夏达奇曼
Give me those coins.Let's try the Dutchman.
好的
Yeah.
友军！
Friendlies!
别开枪！
Hold your fire!
你看到地面部队了吗？
Have you seen ground troops?
听到了吗？
Hear that?
空袭停止了
The bombing's stopped.
守住阵地！
Defensive positions!
行动！
Move out!
-卡琳？ -（他不干）
- Karin? - 'He won't do it.'
妈的！
Fuck!
好了 无论如何还是要谢谢你
All right. Thanks for trying, anyway.
-（你现在打算怎么办？） -我不知道
- 'What are you gonna do now?' - I don't know.
妈的！
Fuck!
我们没事 我会再打给你..卡琳？
We're OK. I'll call you once... Karin?
-现在怎么办？-我们得离开城里 来吧
- Now what? - We've gotta leave town. Come on.
哇！
Whoa!
天啊！
Jesus!
我们走！来！
Let's go! Come on!
他们正在进行最后的扫荡
They're doing a final sweep.
地面部队到达之前我们得找地方避难!
We've got to find shelter before the ground troops get here!
妈的！
Fuck!
嘿！真高兴你们大家没有死！
Hey! So glad you guys didn't die!
你还好吗？
How are you?
嘿！你怎么找到我们的？
Hey! How did you find us?
你的留言 我试着给你回电话
Your message.I tried calling you back.
-你仍然需要卫星上传吗？ -是
- You still need a SAT upload? - Yeah.
-我有一个 我和斯蒂尔顿有卫星通讯车 来吧
I got one. Stilton and I have an upload vehicle. Come on.
我应该把车开过来,不过我感觉会被炸掉
I would've driven it here, but I didn't feel like blowing up.
听着 这次我需要你待在这儿 好吗？
Listen, I need you to sit this one out, OK?
-安德斯 我能照顾我自己 -好的 我们不能冒这个险 求你了！
- Anders, I can take care of myself.- Well, we can't risk this. Please!
我去哪儿能比这儿更安全？
Where am I gonna be safer?
我的电台会帮你们的 来！
My station will take yours. Come on!
等等.我们得绕路走
Hold on. We've got to make a detour.
德米多夫告诉过我他们不炸教堂,所以
Demidov told me they spared the churches, so...
大家 靠近点 靠近
Everybody, get close. Get close.
-现在高兴点 -该死的
- Now be happy. - For fuck's sake!
只是战争而已
It's only a war.
（LAW单兵反坦克火箭筒）
安德斯 我不喜欢这样
Anders... I don't like this at all.
就算为我这么做好吗？
Would you do it for me?
我们很快就回来然后我们一起离开城市
We'll come right back and then we can all leave the city together.
好的
Fine.
谢谢你
Thank you.
如果发生什么事我怎么联系你？
How do I get in touch with you if something happens?
这是达奇曼的手机号.告诉他们
That's Dutchman's cell. Tell these...
问问这些人看看谁有电话
Ask these people if anybody has a cell phone.
好的 号码是多少？
OK. What's the number?
这里
There.
上传完毕后我就给你打这个电话 好吗？
I'll call you on this phone as soon as the upload is done, OK?
好的
OK.
你知道,我希望...
You know, I hope...
-安德斯 来吧！我们走！-来！
- Anders, come on! Let's go! - Come on!
我联系不上斯蒂尔顿 信号不稳定
I can't reach Stilton. The signal keeps coming in and out.
斯蒂尔顿！
Stilton!
-怎么了？-佐伊和他在一起
- What's up? - Zoe's with him.
她知道自己在做什么
She knows what she's doing.
好戏开始了！
Align the dish!
给我们连接支持！快！
Link us back up! Hurry!
醒醒,罗密欧！
Wake up, Romeo!
我们能搞到的就是这些了 人们得看看这录像！现在！
It's all we got. The people have got to see this footage! Now!
给
Here.
希望还能用
Hope it still works.
-文件没有受损. -哦！好啊！
- Data's intact. - Oh, yes!
上传需要多长时间？
How long for the uplink?
-来吧 -大约2分钟
- Come on. - About two minutes to transmit.
-要喝些什么吗？-我要等录像传完
- Can I offer you a drink? - I'll wait till the footage is out.
但我会抽根烟
But I will take a cigarette.
它们瞄准我们了!快找掩护！快！
They've targeted us! Get under cover! Go!
走，走，走！
Go, go, go!
-你在干什么？ -保存我们的录像 走！
- What are you doing? - Saving our footage. Go!
-快到了！-必须走了！
- Almost there! - Gotta go!
快来！
Come on!
-快走！-快！过来！
- Get out! - Come on! Come on!
-我们办不到的！-快走！
- We're not gonna make it! - Get out!
快起来！过来！
Get up now! Come on!
达奇曼？斯蒂尔顿？
Dutchman? Stilton?
赛巴斯蒂安！
Sebastian!
我看起来很糟糕是不是？
It's bad, isn't it?
我感觉不到了！
I can't feel shit!
你没事
You're OK.
嘿
Hey.
哦,妈的.该死
Oh, fuck. Shit.
-走 走 -我不会丢下你的
- Go, go. - I'm not leaving you.
-你必须走 -我能帮你
- You have to go. - I can help you.
-不不.听我说 你必须走 现在
No, no, no. Listen to me.You need to go. Now.
-我他妈不会离开你的！-你他妈闭上嘴好吗？
- I'm not fucking leaving you! - Shut the fuck up, OK?
我动不了了
I can't move.
你得把我们的录像播出去
You have to get our footage out.
回到教堂把存储卡藏好直到安全的时候
Go back to that church.Hide the card until it's safe.
我会没事的
I'll be fine.
最佳承保对象,记得吗？
Life insurance policy. Remember?
听着 你得帮我这个忙
Listen, you have to do this for me.
向我保证 保证你会把录像播出去
Promise me. Promise me you'll get the footage out.
-向我保证！-我保证！
- Promise me! - I promise!
给 拿着这个
Here. Take this.
我马上就回来
I'm coming right back.
走！
Go!
塔蒂亚？
Tatia?
塔蒂亚？刚才和我在一起的女孩去哪儿了？
Tatia? Where is the girl I was with?
拜托给位 肯定有人知道 刚才和我一起的女孩去哪儿了？
Come on, guys. Somebody must know.Where is the girl I was with?
那女孩儿呢？刚才有个女孩和我在一起
Where's the girl? There was a girl with me.
我不需要电话.我要找刚才跟我在一起的女孩儿
I don't need a phone this time. I need the girl I was with.
还记得这女孩吗？
Remember the girl?
哦 天啊
Oh, Jesus.
-如果你伤害她..-来斯大林广场
- 'If you have hurt her...'- Come to the Stalin Square.
把存储卡带来
Bring the memory card.
我需要你帮我做一件重要的事
I need you to do something very important for me.
你明白吗？好的
Do you understand? OK.
你带来我要的东西了吗？
Did you bring what I wanted?
放她走
Let her go.
感谢上帝！
Thank God!
-你还好吗？-是的
- You all right? - Yeah.
我以为再也见不到你了
I thought I'd never see you again.
你播出去了吗？
Did you make the broadcast?
没有
No.
赛巴斯蒂安呢？
Sebastian?
也没有
No.
一切都会好起来的
Everything will be OK.
我真希望能更了解你
I would have liked to know you better.
我不明白
I don't understand.
现在我要你赶快跑
Now I need you to run.
-安德斯... -走 走吧
- Anders... - Go. Go.
快跑！
Go!
密码是1216
The code is 1216.
（没有数据）
在艾威奈维你搜我身的时候落了张卡
You missed a card when you searched me Avnevi.
真正的卡已经由一位勇敢的小女孩
The real one's on its way to a human rights group,
送往人权组织了
courtesy of a brave little girl.
都结束了
It's over.
你凭什么觉得你能活下来?
And how did you think you could survive this?
我没有
I didn't.
我想我已经告诉过你要跑了!
I thought I told you to run!
我想要见他最后一次,好吗?
I wanna see him one last time, OK?
这是..
This...
这是我离开他的地方
This is where I left him.
我他妈离开他了
I fucking left him.
安德斯！
Anders!
-嘿,里佐! -我们需要你的帮助
- Hey, Rezo! - We need your help.
-好的 -很好
- OK.- Right.
-安德斯 -赛巴斯蒂安?
- Anders.- Sebastian?
-赛巴斯蒂安!这是怎么回事?
Sebastian! What the fuck?
-我装死的 -你还好吗?
- I played dead. - Are you OK?
-我们能移动你吗? -能
- Can we move you? - Yeah.
我们来带他离开这儿,来
Let's get him out of here.come on
-你还好吗 兄弟? -是的
- You all right, bucko? - Yeah.
等一下,我们必须停下来.把他放下
Hold on, we gotta stop. Put him down.
不要抵抗了,上尉
Don't resist, Captain.
-安德斯? -在这儿我们无处可逃了
- Anders?- There's nowhere to run.
即使我们
Even if we could.
长官,他们没有抵抗
Sir, they're not resisting.
离开这儿!
Get away from here!
走!
Go!
这里的杀戮已经够多了
There's been enough killing.
今天侵略者在我们的国门前聚集
Today the forces of occupation have gathered at our gates.
我们知道那个帝国非常的强大
And we know that this empire is very powerful.
他们有很多的坦克 他们有很多的飞机
They have lots of tanks. They have lots of planes.
但是我们有更为珍贵的东西
But we have something that is more precious.
我们有对自由的热爱,我们有对独立的热爱!
We have the love for freedom, and we have the love for independence!
今天我们站在这里为国家的独立而自豪
We stand here today as one proud independent nation.
就像我们之前的芬兰人,捷克人和匈牙利人
Just like the Finns, just like the Czechs,and just like the Hungarians before us.
今天我们在全世界面前告诉他们
And we tell them today,in front of the whole world,
自由不会退缩,自由不会投降!
that freedom will not retreat,freedom will not surrender!
我们可能被包围了,但是我们并不孤单
We may be besieged,but we are not alone.
今晚六个欧洲国家的总统和我们站在一起
Standing with us here tonight are six European presidents
他们跋涉了数千英里
who have travelled thousands of miles
来和我们一起反抗恐惧和威胁!
in defiance of fear and threats!
他们六位在这里是因为他们知道独立问题
These six men are here because they know the issue of independence
今晚将会在这里解决!
is being decided here tonight!
愿上帝保佑格鲁吉亚人民,格鲁吉亚自由万岁!
May God bless the Georgian people! Long live a free Georgia!
格鲁吉亚!格鲁吉亚!格鲁吉亚!
Georgia! Georgia! Georgia!
他们说你会完全康复的
They say you're gonna make a full recovery.
是吗?6个月!
Yeah? Six months!
还有..我们的录像?
And... our footage?
送出去了.正在人权组织那儿
It's out. Human Rights Watch has it.
反响很大 很多人都开始关注了
It's getting a lot of hits and people are starting to pay attention.
就像开炮
Not bad for a loose cannon.
谢谢,兄弟
Thanks, bucko.
(尽管已经停火并承诺撤军)
'Despite the ceasefire and pledges to withdraw,
(俄罗斯军队和坦克仍然停留在哥里)
'the Russian troops and tanks remain in Gori,
(以及格鲁吉亚中部的大片区域)
'and in much of central Georgia.
(我现在正站在军医院)
'I am standing at the military hospital
(人们被陆续转移到达这里)
'where displaced people continue to arrive.
(人们没有其它地方可去)
'People with nowhere else to go,
(除了暴力,掠夺和杀戮的情景以外什么也没有)
'and nothing but stories of violence, looting and killings.
战争持续了5天
The war lasted five days.
(有超过10万人失去了他们的家园)
'More than 100,000 people have lost their homes...
(数百人被杀害,包括5名记者)
Several hundred people were killed,including five reporters.
(自战争爆发后的9天以来)
'...since this war began just nine days ago.
(人们总是问我怎么仍然会发生这样的事)
'People keep asking me how can this still be happening...'
估计有5万人无家可归
An estimated 50,000 people were made homeless,
他们的村庄被侵占或遭到了永久性的破坏
their villages permanently destroyed or occupied.
很多人仍然在难民营居住
Many still live in refugee camps.
尽管美国和欧洲要求撤军
Despite demands from Europe and the United States to withdraw,
南奥塞梯和阿布哈兹地区仍然被俄军侵占
the regions of South Ossetia and Abkhazia remain occupied by Russian forces.
此刻这个国家正在为它的生存而战
This nation is right now fighting for its survival.
格鲁吉亚继续寻求与西方融为一体
Georgia continues its quest to integrate with the West.
(这是托马斯.安德斯在格鲁吉亚发回的报道)
'This is Thomas Anders reporting in Georgia.'
我的丈夫,米哈伊尔.塔波什维利,在艾瑞提村被杀害
My husband, Mikheil Taboshvili.Killed in Eredvi village.
我的爸爸
My father.
我的婆婆,纳塔利亚.欧克罗派莱德兹
My mother-in-law, Natalia Okropiridze.
我的母亲,纳塔利亚.欧克罗派莱德兹
My mother, Natalia Okropiridze.
在疏散时我父母正在穿过公路
As my parents were being evacuated and they were crossing the road,
一颗地雷在他们的车前爆炸 弹片直接击中了她的太阳穴
a mine exploded in front of their car and shrapnel hit her straight in the temple.
她当场死亡
She died on the spot.
泽巴辛德兹.塔玛尔,我的母亲
Zambakhidze Tamar, my mother.
我的妻子
My wife.
我们的祖母
Our grandmother.
我的父母被拷问,他们被割开了喉咙
My parents were tortured.Their throats were slit.
他们被埋在我的后院,这就是我知道的一切
They were buried in our backyard,and that's all we know.
这是诺达尔.奥提阿什维利,我的父亲
This is Nodar Otiashvili, my father.
我们以前住在卡维默阿查贝提村
We used to live in Kvemo Achabeti village.
我是斯科莱特.戈德兹的儿子
I am the son of Socrate Gogidze.
红十字会的人告诉我
I was told by the Red Cross
他被埋在我家的花园里
that he was buried in our garden.
他是被吊死的
He had been hanged.
我是玛丽娜.卡比阿什维利.我过去住在克海维村
I am Marina Kakhbiashvili.I used to live in Kehvi village.
在8月8日那天,我们离开了
On August 8th, we left.
我的丈夫留在那儿.我的儿子和我丈夫
My husband stayed there.My son and my husband.
我儿子那天晚上离开了.我丈夫永远留在了屋子里
My son left that night.My husband stayed in the house.
埃卡特琳.帕普利什维利,我的祖母
Ekaterine Papelishvili, my grandmother.